http://www.univiu.org/about-viu-footer/privacy-policy

Venice International University use cookies to give you the best possible experience
By using our website, you agree to our use of cookies.												Lear more
I agree
Search ...
Log in
Forgot your username?
Forgot your password?
About VIUWhat is VIU?MembersGovernancePresidentDeanBoard of DirectorsAcademic CouncilStatuteTransparent Administration (L.231)OrganizationAcademic ProgramsTEN ProgramTeDIS ProgramAgeing ProgramVIU StaffQuality Management System CertificationRegional AccreditationNetworks & PartnershipsAlcantara SpAEuropelagoGUPESUN Global CompactSDSN ASvISDistretto Veneziano della Ricerca e dell'InnovazioneBrochures, Reports and RegulationsHistory of San Servolo StudyGlobalization ProgramCoursesAdmissionsAcademic CalendarSchedulesScholarshipsStudent guideInternshipsTeaching at VIUVisiting professorsPeopleGP NewsPhD Academy2021 | What is a People? Social, Political and Legal Controversies2021 | Plastic Pollution and Bioplastic Materials2021 | Light: Its Nature and Its Use2021 | Cities and Water in a Time of Climate Change2021 | Everything you always wanted to know about becoming a researcher2021 | Quantitative Methods in Legal StudiesGraduate Seminars2021 | Activism and Social Movements2021 | Climate Change Mitigation: Carbon Capture and UtilizationSummer/Autumn/Winter Schools2021 | LIVES Life Course and Vulnerabilities2021 | Ageing2021 | After Capitalism2021 | Advanced Transportation, Logistics and Supply Chain Management2021 | Global Shakespeare: Othello’s Venice in the World2021 | Migration and Gender: a Legal and Literary Perspective2021 | Critical Infrastructure Resilience2021 | Science Diplomacy2021 | Films in Venice and Filming VeniceMembers' Autonomous ProgramsFocus AreasGreen & Circular EconomyEnvironmental Management and SecurityScience Communication and EducationSustainable LogisticsWhat We Do in Sustainable LogisticsCreativity, Innovation and DesignWhat We Do in Creativity, Innovation and DesignAgeingCultural HeritageGlobal Challenges InitiativesProjects ArchiveVIULifeLectiones Magistrales & VIULecturesWhat's New at VIU NewsletterVIU NewsSocial Media WallVIU OpportunitiesCo-curricular Program for StudentsVirtual ExchangeVIU People ProfilesPhoto Galleries/MultimediaAlumni, Fellows & FriendsContact FormGive to VIUVIU FellowsVisiting researchersInternships at the Biennale di VeneziaExperiencing China 2018 | Tsinghua University Summer SchoolJapanese Studies | Summer Session | Waseda UniversityISPM China – International Summer Program in Management Guangzhou UniversityVeUMEU 2018 - Venice Universities' Model European UnionVeUMEU 2018 application form Cosmopolitan Views of Law - Talks in memory of Prof. Hiroshi NishiharaCampus & ServicesMapsConferences in San ServoloUpcoming Conferences2018 ConferencesPast ConferencesConference RoomsCampus FacilitiesClassroomsPC RoomMacLabHow to get to VIUNetwork accessLibraryAccommodationelearning - moodleVisa OfficeCapacity buildingSino Italian TrainingCourse for SustainabilityExcellence in CBSummer Training Course on Circular Economy: Policies and Practices21st International Society for Business Innovation and Technology Management ConferenceEuropean Project Training UnitAdvanced Training Program on Local Sustainable Development for Mexico City Government4th International Symposium on Sustainability4th International Symposium_application formMOBIS – Modelli di Business per l’Innovazione Sociale
Workshop: Social Innovation, Sustainability and GrowthISRE CUBE project Policy and incentives for Science Communication WorkshopTrain the Scientist!Open Africa Power ProgramErasmus+ study grants for students of Italian member universities
About VIUWhat is VIU?MembersGovernancePresidentDeanBoard of DirectorsAcademic CouncilStatuteTransparent Administration (L.231)OrganizationAcademic ProgramsTEN ProgramTeDIS ProgramAgeing ProgramVIU StaffQuality Management System CertificationRegional AccreditationNetworks & PartnershipsAlcantara SpAEuropelagoGUPESUN Global CompactSDSN ASvISDistretto Veneziano della Ricerca e dell'InnovazioneBrochures, Reports and RegulationsHistory of San Servolo StudyGlobalization ProgramCoursesAdmissionsAcademic CalendarSchedulesScholarshipsStudent guideInternshipsTeaching at VIUVisiting professorsPeopleGP NewsPhD Academy2021 | What is a People? Social, Political and Legal Controversies2021 | Plastic Pollution and Bioplastic Materials2021 | Light: Its Nature and Its Use2021 | Cities and Water in a Time of Climate Change2021 | Everything you always wanted to know about becoming a researcher2021 | Quantitative Methods in Legal StudiesGraduate Seminars2021 | Activism and Social Movements2021 | Climate Change Mitigation: Carbon Capture and UtilizationSummer/Autumn/Winter Schools2021 | LIVES Life Course and Vulnerabilities2021 | Ageing2021 | After Capitalism2021 | Advanced Transportation, Logistics and Supply Chain Management2021 | Global Shakespeare: Othello’s Venice in the World2021 | Migration and Gender: a Legal and Literary Perspective2021 | Critical Infrastructure Resilience2021 | Science Diplomacy2021 | Films in Venice and Filming VeniceMembers' Autonomous ProgramsFocus AreasGreen & Circular EconomyEnvironmental Management and SecurityScience Communication and EducationSustainable LogisticsWhat We Do in Sustainable LogisticsCreativity, Innovation and DesignWhat We Do in Creativity, Innovation and DesignAgeingCultural HeritageGlobal Challenges InitiativesProjects ArchiveVIULifeLectiones Magistrales & VIULecturesWhat's New at VIU NewsletterVIU NewsSocial Media WallVIU OpportunitiesCo-curricular Program for StudentsVirtual ExchangeVIU People ProfilesPhoto Galleries/MultimediaAlumni, Fellows & FriendsContact FormGive to VIUVIU FellowsVisiting researchersInternships at the Biennale di VeneziaExperiencing China 2018 | Tsinghua University Summer SchoolJapanese Studies | Summer Session | Waseda UniversityISPM China – International Summer Program in Management Guangzhou UniversityVeUMEU 2018 - Venice Universities' Model European UnionVeUMEU 2018 application form Cosmopolitan Views of Law - Talks in memory of Prof. Hiroshi NishiharaCampus & ServicesMapsConferences in San ServoloUpcoming Conferences2018 ConferencesPast ConferencesConference RoomsCampus FacilitiesClassroomsPC RoomMacLabHow to get to VIUNetwork accessLibraryAccommodationelearning - moodleVisa OfficeCapacity buildingSino Italian TrainingCourse for SustainabilityExcellence in CBSummer Training Course on Circular Economy: Policies and Practices21st International Society for Business Innovation and Technology Management ConferenceEuropean Project Training UnitAdvanced Training Program on Local Sustainable Development for Mexico City Government4th International Symposium on Sustainability4th International Symposium_application formMOBIS – Modelli di Business per l’Innovazione Sociale
Workshop: Social Innovation, Sustainability and GrowthISRE CUBE project Policy and incentives for Science Communication WorkshopTrain the Scientist!Open Africa Power ProgramErasmus+ study grants for students of Italian member universities
Venice International University Policy on Data Protection
Contents1. Purpose and scope.2. Principles. 3. Aims and commitments. 4. Roles and responsibilities. 5. Breaches of data privacy legislation. 6. Compliance. 7. Further information. 8. Review and development 9. Related policies and notices.
1. Purpose and scopeThis policy provides a framework for ensuring that Venice International University (VIU) meets its obligations under the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) and associated legislation .It applies to all processing of personal data carried out for a VIU purpose, irrespective of whether the data is processed on non-university equipment or by third parties.‘Personal data’ means any information relating to an identifiable living individual who can be identified from that data or from that data and other data. ‘Processing’ means anything that is done with personal data, including collection, storage, use, disclosure and deletion.More stringent conditions apply to the processing of special category personal data (sensitive data under Italian legislation 196/2003).‘Special category’ means personal data revealing racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, religious or philosophical beliefs, or trade union membership, and the processing of genetic data, biometric data for the purpose of uniquely identifying an individual, data concerning health or data concerning an individual’s sex life or sexual orientation.This policy does not cover the use of personal data by staff of Venice International University when acting in a private or non-VIU capacity.2. PrinciplesThe processing of personal data must comply with data privacy legislation and, in particular, the six data privacy principles of GDPR. In summary, they require that personal data is:• processed fairly, lawfully and in a transparent manner;• used only for limited, specified stated purposes and not used or disclosed in any way incompatible with those purposes;• adequate, relevant and limited to what is necessary;• accurate and, where necessary, up-to-date;• not kept for longer than necessary; and• kept safe and secure.In addition, a new accountability principle requires VIU to be able to evidence compliance with these principles.
3. Aims and commitmentsVIU handles a considerable amount of personal data and takes seriously its responsibilities under data privacy legislation. It recognizes that the mishandling of an individual’s personal data may cause them distress or put them at risk of identity fraud. As a result, it is committed to:• complying fully with data privacy legislation;• adhering to good practice, as issued by the Italian Data Protection Authority and any other appropriate bodies; • handling an individual’s personal data in a careful and considerate manner that recognizes the importance of such information to their privacy and welfare.VIU seeks to achieve these aims by:• ensuring that staff, students and other individuals who process data for VIU purposes are made aware of their individual responsibilities under data privacy legislation and how these apply to their areas of work. • providing suitable training, guidance and advice. • incorporating data privacy requirements into administrative procedures where these involve the processing of personal data, particularly in relation to major information systems (the principle of ‘privacy by design’);• operating a centrally coordinated procedure (in order to ensure consistency) for the processing rights based requests made by individuals (eg. right of erasure); • investigating promptly any suspected breach of data privacy legislation; reporting it, where necessary, to the Italian Data Protection Authority; and seeking to learn any lessons from the incident in order to reduce the risk of reoccurrence.Furthermore:• data privacy risks and responsibilities are included in the VIU Organizational, Management and Control Model, pursuant to Legislative Decree no. 231 of June 8, 2001, which sets out the rules for the administrative liability of Bodies, Companies and Associations and which was adopted by the VIU Board of Directors on April 26, 2014. • The VIU Code of Ethics, also adopted on April 26, 2014 is an integral and complementary part of the 231/2001 Model, and includes principles of business ethics and rules of conduct that VIU recognizes as its own and that its corporate bodies and employees must observe.
4. Roles and responsibilitiesThe PresidentThe President has executive responsibility for ensuring that VIU complies with data privacy legislation.
Information Compliance TeamThe Information Compliance Team is responsible for:• establishing and maintaining policies and procedures at a central level to facilitate the VIU’s compliance with data privacy legislation;• establishing and maintaining guidance and training materials on data privacy legislation and specific compliance issues;• supporting privacy by design and privacy impact assessments;• responding to requests for advice from departments;• coordinating a register to track the full range of processing that is carried out;• complying with rights-based requests made by individuals;• investigating and responding to complaints regarding data protection (including requests to cease the processing of personal data); and• keeping records of personal data breaches, notifying the Data Protection Authority of any significant breaches and responding to any requests that it may make for further information.In fulfilling these responsibilities, the team may also involve, and draw on support from, representatives from VIU offices, programs and units.
Executive Directors of Programs (or equivalent)Executive Directors of Programs are responsible for ensuring that the processing of personal data in their department conforms to the requirements of data privacy legislation and this policy. In particular, they must ensure that:• new and existing staff, visitors or third parties associated with the Department who are likely to process personal data are aware of their responsibilities under data privacy legislation. This includes drawing the attention of staff to the requirements of this policy, ensuring that staff who have responsibility for handling personal data are provided with adequate training and, where appropriate, ensuring that job descriptions for members of staff or agreements with relevant third parties reference data privacy responsibilities. • adequate records of processing activities are kept (for example, by undertaking register exercises);• data protection requirements are embedded into systems and processes by adopting a ‘privacy by design’ approach and undertaking privacy impact assessments where appropriate;• privacy notices are provided where data is collected directly from individuals or where data is used in non-standard ways;• data sharing is conducted in accordance with VIU guidance;• requests from the Information Compliance Team for information are complied with promptly;
Others processing personal data for a VIU purpose eg. staff, students, interns and volunteers
Anyone who processes personal data for a VIU purpose is individually responsible for complying with data privacy legislation, this policy and any other policy, guidance, procedures, and/or training introduced by VIU to comply with data privacy legislation. In summary, they must ensure that they:• only use personal data in ways people would expect and for the purposes for which it was collected;• use a minimum amount of personal data and only hold it for as long as is strictly necessary;• keep personal data up-to-date;• keep personal data secure, in accordance with the VIU’s Information Technology Security Measures;• do not disclose personal data to unauthorized persons, whether inside or outside VIU;• complete relevant training as required;• report promptly any suspected breaches of data privacy legislation, in accordance with the procedure in section 6 below, and following any recommended next steps;• seek advice from the Information Compliance Team where they are unsure how to comply with data privacy legislation; and• promptly respond to any requests from the Information Compliance Team in connection with subject access and other rights based requests and complaints (and forward any such requests that are received directly to the Information Compliance Team promptly).
5. Breaches of data privacy legislationVIU will investigate incidents involving a possible breach of data privacy legislation in order to ensure that, where necessary, appropriate action is taken to mitigate the consequences and prevent a repetition of similar incidents in future. Depending on the nature and severity of the incident, it may also be necessary to notify the individuals affected and/or the Data Protection Agency. A breach will occur where, for example, personal data is disclosed or made available to unauthorized persons or personal data is used in a way that the individual does not expect.Incidents involving failures of IT systems or processes must be reported the Information Security Team as soon as they are discovered (information.security@univiu.org).All other incidents must be reported directly to the Information Compliance Team at the earliest possible opportunity (data.protection@univiu.org).
6. ComplianceVIU regards any breach of data privacy legislation, this policy or any other policy and/or training introduced by VIU from time to time to comply with data privacy legislation as a serious matter, which may result in disciplinary action. Depending on the nature of the breach, an individual may also find that they are personally liable (for example, it can be a criminal offence for a member of VIU to disclose personal information unlawfully).
7. Further informationQuestions about this policy and data privacy matters in general should be directed to the Information Compliance Team at: data.protection@univiu.org Questions about information security should be directed to the Information Security Team at: information.security@univiu.org
8. Review and developmentThis policy, and supporting guidance, will apply with effect from 25 May 2018. Any revisions or updates will be published on the VIU website.
9. Related policies and noticesThis policy should be read in conjunction with related policies and regulations, including the:• VIU Organizational, Management and Control Model, pursuant to Legislative Decree no. 231 of June 8, 2001• VIU Code of Ethics • VIU Minimum Security Measures relative to terms of access and use of the IT network at VIU.• Data Protection Notice for Students of Globalization Program• Data Protection Notice for Academic Programs (other than Globalization Program) • Data Protection Notice for Users of VIU website www.univiu.org• Data Protection Notice for recipients of VIU Communications • Data Protection Notice for Erasmus+ mobility applicants• Data Protection Notice for Subscribers to viucommunity
Last updated 09 April 2020
Contents1. Purpose and scope.2. Principles. 3. Aims and commitments. 4. Roles and responsibilities. 5. Breaches of data privacy legislation. 6. Compliance. 7. Further information. 8. Review and development 9. Related policies and notices.
1. Purpose and scopeThis policy provides a framework for ensuring that Venice International University (VIU) meets its obligations under the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) and associated legislation .It applies to all processing of personal data carried out for a VIU purpose, irrespective of whether the data is processed on non-university equipment or by third parties.‘Personal data’ means any information relating to an identifiable living individual who can be identified from that data or from that data and other data. ‘Processing’ means anything that is done with personal data, including collection, storage, use, disclosure and deletion.More stringent conditions apply to the processing of special category personal data (sensitive data under Italian legislation 196/2003).‘Special category’ means personal data revealing racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, religious or philosophical beliefs, or trade union membership, and the processing of genetic data, biometric data for the purpose of uniquely identifying an individual, data concerning health or data concerning an individual’s sex life or sexual orientation.This policy does not cover the use of personal data by staff of Venice International University when acting in a private or non-VIU capacity.2. PrinciplesThe processing of personal data must comply with data privacy legislation and, in particular, the six data privacy principles of GDPR. In summary, they require that personal data is:• processed fairly, lawfully and in a transparent manner;• used only for limited, specified stated purposes and not used or disclosed in any way incompatible with those purposes;• adequate, relevant and limited to what is necessary;• accurate and, where necessary, up-to-date;• not kept for longer than necessary; and• kept safe and secure.In addition, a new accountability principle requires VIU to be able to evidence compliance with these principles.
3. Aims and commitmentsVIU handles a considerable amount of personal data and takes seriously its responsibilities under data privacy legislation. It recognizes that the mishandling of an individual’s personal data may cause them distress or put them at risk of identity fraud. As a result, it is committed to:• complying fully with data privacy legislation;• adhering to good practice, as issued by the Italian Data Protection Authority and any other appropriate bodies; • handling an individual’s personal data in a careful and considerate manner that recognizes the importance of such information to their privacy and welfare.VIU seeks to achieve these aims by:• ensuring that staff, students and other individuals who process data for VIU purposes are made aware of their individual responsibilities under data privacy legislation and how these apply to their areas of work. • providing suitable training, guidance and advice. • incorporating data privacy requirements into administrative procedures where these involve the processing of personal data, particularly in relation to major information systems (the principle of ‘privacy by design’);• operating a centrally coordinated procedure (in order to ensure consistency) for the processing rights based requests made by individuals (eg. right of erasure); • investigating promptly any suspected breach of data privacy legislation; reporting it, where necessary, to the Italian Data Protection Authority; and seeking to learn any lessons from the incident in order to reduce the risk of reoccurrence.Furthermore:• data privacy risks and responsibilities are included in the VIU Organizational, Management and Control Model, pursuant to Legislative Decree no. 231 of June 8, 2001, which sets out the rules for the administrative liability of Bodies, Companies and Associations and which was adopted by the VIU Board of Directors on April 26, 2014. • The VIU Code of Ethics, also adopted on April 26, 2014 is an integral and complementary part of the 231/2001 Model, and includes principles of business ethics and rules of conduct that VIU recognizes as its own and that its corporate bodies and employees must observe.
4. Roles and responsibilitiesThe PresidentThe President has executive responsibility for ensuring that VIU complies with data privacy legislation.
Information Compliance TeamThe Information Compliance Team is responsible for:• establishing and maintaining policies and procedures at a central level to facilitate the VIU’s compliance with data privacy legislation;• establishing and maintaining guidance and training materials on data privacy legislation and specific compliance issues;• supporting privacy by design and privacy impact assessments;• responding to requests for advice from departments;• coordinating a register to track the full range of processing that is carried out;• complying with rights-based requests made by individuals;• investigating and responding to complaints regarding data protection (including requests to cease the processing of personal data); and• keeping records of personal data breaches, notifying the Data Protection Authority of any significant breaches and responding to any requests that it may make for further information.In fulfilling these responsibilities, the team may also involve, and draw on support from, representatives from VIU offices, programs and units.
Executive Directors of Programs (or equivalent)Executive Directors of Programs are responsible for ensuring that the processing of personal data in their department conforms to the requirements of data privacy legislation and this policy. In particular, they must ensure that:• new and existing staff, visitors or third parties associated with the Department who are likely to process personal data are aware of their responsibilities under data privacy legislation. This includes drawing the attention of staff to the requirements of this policy, ensuring that staff who have responsibility for handling personal data are provided with adequate training and, where appropriate, ensuring that job descriptions for members of staff or agreements with relevant third parties reference data privacy responsibilities. • adequate records of processing activities are kept (for example, by undertaking register exercises);• data protection requirements are embedded into systems and processes by adopting a ‘privacy by design’ approach and undertaking privacy impact assessments where appropriate;• privacy notices are provided where data is collected directly from individuals or where data is used in non-standard ways;• data sharing is conducted in accordance with VIU guidance;• requests from the Information Compliance Team for information are complied with promptly;
Others processing personal data for a VIU purpose eg. staff, students, interns and volunteers
Anyone who processes personal data for a VIU purpose is individually responsible for complying with data privacy legislation, this policy and any other policy, guidance, procedures, and/or training introduced by VIU to comply with data privacy legislation. In summary, they must ensure that they:• only use personal data in ways people would expect and for the purposes for which it was collected;• use a minimum amount of personal data and only hold it for as long as is strictly necessary;• keep personal data up-to-date;• keep personal data secure, in accordance with the VIU’s Information Technology Security Measures;• do not disclose personal data to unauthorized persons, whether inside or outside VIU;• complete relevant training as required;• report promptly any suspected breaches of data privacy legislation, in accordance with the procedure in section 6 below, and following any recommended next steps;• seek advice from the Information Compliance Team where they are unsure how to comply with data privacy legislation; and• promptly respond to any requests from the Information Compliance Team in connection with subject access and other rights based requests and complaints (and forward any such requests that are received directly to the Information Compliance Team promptly).
5. Breaches of data privacy legislationVIU will investigate incidents involving a possible breach of data privacy legislation in order to ensure that, where necessary, appropriate action is taken to mitigate the consequences and prevent a repetition of similar incidents in future. Depending on the nature and severity of the incident, it may also be necessary to notify the individuals affected and/or the Data Protection Agency. A breach will occur where, for example, personal data is disclosed or made available to unauthorized persons or personal data is used in a way that the individual does not expect.Incidents involving failures of IT systems or processes must be reported the Information Security Team as soon as they are discovered (information.security@univiu.org).All other incidents must be reported directly to the Information Compliance Team at the earliest possible opportunity (data.protection@univiu.org).
6. ComplianceVIU regards any breach of data privacy legislation, this policy or any other policy and/or training introduced by VIU from time to time to comply with data privacy legislation as a serious matter, which may result in disciplinary action. Depending on the nature of the breach, an individual may also find that they are personally liable (for example, it can be a criminal offence for a member of VIU to disclose personal information unlawfully).
7. Further informationQuestions about this policy and data privacy matters in general should be directed to the Information Compliance Team at: data.protection@univiu.org Questions about information security should be directed to the Information Security Team at: information.security@univiu.org
8. Review and developmentThis policy, and supporting guidance, will apply with effect from 25 May 2018. Any revisions or updates will be published on the VIU website.
9. Related policies and noticesThis policy should be read in conjunction with related policies and regulations, including the:• VIU Organizational, Management and Control Model, pursuant to Legislative Decree no. 231 of June 8, 2001• VIU Code of Ethics • VIU Minimum Security Measures relative to terms of access and use of the IT network at VIU.• Data Protection Notice for Students of Globalization Program• Data Protection Notice for Academic Programs (other than Globalization Program) • Data Protection Notice for Users of VIU website www.univiu.org• Data Protection Notice for recipients of VIU Communications • Data Protection Notice for Erasmus+ mobility applicants• Data Protection Notice for Subscribers to viucommunity
Last updated 09 April 2020
VeniceInternationalUniversity
Isola di San Servolo 30133 Venice, Italy
- phone: +39 041 2719511 fax:+39 041 2719510 email: viu@univiu.org
VAT: 02928970272
About VIU
MembersGovernanceOrganizationAcademic ProgramsTEN ProgramTeDIS ProgramAgeing ProgramNetworks & PartnershipsGive to VIUData Protection Policy
Study
Globalization ProgramPhD AcademyGraduate SeminarsSummer/Autumn/Winter SchoolsMembers' Autonomous Programs
Focus Areas
Green & Circular EconomyEnvironmental Management and SecurityScience Communication and EducationSustainable LogisticsCreativity, Innovation and DesignAgeingCultural HeritageGlobal Challenges InitiativesProjects Archive
VIU life
Lectiones Magistrales & VIULecturesWhat's New at VIU NewsletterVIU NewsSocial Media WallVIU OpportunitiesCo-curricular Program for StudentsVIU People ProfilesPhoto Galleries/MultimediaAlumni, Fellows & FriendsVisiting researchersInternships at the Biennale di VeneziaExperiencing China 2018 | Tsinghua University Summer SchoolJapanese Studies | Summer Session | Waseda UniversityISPM China – International Summer Program in Management Guangzhou UniversityVeUMEU 2018 - Venice Universities' Model European Union Cosmopolitan Views of Law - Talks in memory of Prof. Hiroshi Nishihara
Campus Services
MapsConferences in San ServoloCampus FacilitiesHow to get to VIUNetwork accessLibraryAccommodationelearning - moodleVisa Office
